Guide to the Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.) Records, 1901-1998 and undated RL.00815
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.) records
1901-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.)
RL.00815
19.9 Linear Feet
Durham, N.C. hospital established in 1901 Dr. Aaron Moore, Dr. Stanford Warren, and John Merrick to serve African Americans in the area. The Lincoln Hospital Records span the years 1901-1998, and primarily comprise the institution's administrative and medical files. The administrative records document the hospital's administrative history from the 1930s to the 1980s (bulk 1950-1976), primarily in files maintained by the hospital superintendents, especially Larry T. Suitt (1963-1977). There is also some information on the Lincoln Hospital School of Nursing. The medical records (1925-1983 and undated) include obstetrical, surgical, discharge, and death records. Some of these are currently closed to research. The collection as a whole documents the bi-racial cooperation that was involved in establishing, running, and maintaining the institution, and outlines the collaboration between Lincoln Hospital, Watts Hospital, and the Duke University School of Medicine in providing patient care as well as education for African American medical professionals. The medical records also demonstrate the emphasis superintendents placed on general record-keeping, statistics, and the documentation of a patient's medical history. Included is a Duke Endowment series that documents the funds the Endowment distributed annually to assist the hospital in meeting costs incurred by charity cases, equipment, and renovations. There are only a few items dated after the merger in 1976 and only one file regarding the institution's School of Nursing.
Access Restrictions
Records containing personally-identifiable medical information are closed to research and are segregated from open materials.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.) Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2003.
Historical Note
Chronology
August 1901 Washington Duke covered construction costs and provided an initial $5,000 endowment Hospital founded by Dr. Aaron Moore, Dr. Stanford Warren, and John Merrick; opened with 50 beds, admitting patients regardless of their ability to pay
1901-1923 Dr. Aaron Moore served as hospital superintendent
1922 Original facility burned down
1923-1934 Dr. Charles Shepard served as hospital superintendent
1925 Second Lincoln Hospital opened
1934-1959 William Rich served as hospital superintendent
1960-1967 Frank W. Scott served as hospital superintendent
1967-1968 Ronald C. Foreman, hospital superintendent
1968-1976 Larry T. Suitt, hospital superintendent
1976 Hospital closed and merged with the Durham County Hospital Corporation
Collection Overview
The Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.) Records, 1901-1998 and undated (bulk 1930-1976), primarily comprise the institution's administrative and medical files. The administrative records document the hospital's administrative history (bulk 1950-1976), primarily in files maintained by the hospital superintendents, especially Larry T. Suitt (1963-1977). There is also some information on the Lincoln Hospital School of Nursing. The medical records (1925-1983 and undated) include obstetrical, surgical, discharge, and death records. Many of the records are currently closed to research as they contain personally-identifiable medical information, but there are some records that are open.
The collection as a whole documents the biracial cooperation that was involved in establishing, running, and maintaining the institution, and outlines the collaboration between Lincoln Hospital, Watts Hospital, and the Duke University School of Medicine in providing patient care as well as education for African American medical professionals. The medical records also demonstrate the emphasis superintendents placed on general record-keeping, statistics, and the documentation of a patient's medical history. Included is a Duke Endowment series that documents the funds the Endowment distributed annually to assist the hospital in meeting costs incurred by charity cases, equipment, and renovations. There are only a few items dated after the merger in 1976 and only one file regarding the institution's School of Nursing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Medical records containing personally-identifiable information such as names, ages, social security numbers, addresses, and case information are currently closed to use and have been segregated. Medical records with no personally-identifiable information are open for use. The collection has been screened for such records, but there may still be information in the collection that falls under the HIPAA Act or other privacy laws. For information on access to these records, please contact Research Services in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Related Material
Robert Edward Dawson Papers, 1939-1998 (Lincoln Hospital board member)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke Endowment Archives Records, 1902-2008 (bulk 1925-2006)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Charles DeWitt Watts Papers, 1917-2004 and undated (Chief of Surgery at Lincoln Hospital)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
African Americans -- Hospital care; African Americans -- Medical care; African Americans -- Medicine; African Americans in the professions; Health services accessibility—United States; African American physicians -- North Carolina; Hospitals -- North Carolina; Medical care -- Utilization -- United States; Durham (N.C.) -- History; African Americans -- Health and hygiene; Duke Endowment; Duke University. School of Medicine; Suitt, Larry T.; Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.); Watts Hospital (Durham, N.C.)
- Hospital Administrator's Files Series, 1963-1977 and n.d (bulk 1968-1976), 1650 items, 2.6 linear feet
  - Joint Executive Committee, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Medical Staff Minutes, 1968-1975 and undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Loose material, undated (Box 1)
  - Joint Executive Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Medical Staff Minutes, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee DCHC, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Development Committee, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee DCHC, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Planning Committee DCHC, 1963-1975 (bulk 1975) (Box 1)
  - Planning Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Building and Grounds Committee, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Planning Committee, 1975 and undated (Box 1)
  - Education Committee DCHC, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - DCH Corporation, 1975-1976 and undated (Box 1)
  - Executive Council Committee, 1975-1976 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Filing System Materials, ca. 1973 (Box 2)
  - Executive Council Committee, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Bylaws, 1975, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Pharmacy and Therapeutics Committee Meeting, 1968-1973, 1976 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Economic Stabilization Program Bulletins, 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Education Committee, Education Sub-Committee, Executive Committee, 1972-1975, folder 1 of 3 (Box 2)
  - Education Committee, Education Sub-Committee, Executive Committee, 1972-1975, folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 3)
  - Revised Bylaws, Rules and Regulations, ca. 1970 (Box 3)
  - Lincoln Log and Miscellaneous, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Hospital and Medical Staff Laws and Bylaws, ca. 1975, 3 folders (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Includes a Quality Review Center Seminar on the Accountability of Health Care Providers; Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals]
  - Durham County Hospital Corporation Development Committee, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Pension Committee, Trustee Development, Ad Hoc Committee Trustees, Joint Conference, 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Building, Grounds Planning Committee, 1973-1975 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Finance Committee, 1975-1977, folder 1 of 5 (Box 3)
  - Finance Committee, 1975-1977, folders 2-5 of 5 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Loose Materials, 1975-1976, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1971-1975, folders 1-3 of 5 (Box 4)
    [Includes some Data Processing Steering Committee Minutes, 1974-1975]
  - Board of Trustees, 1971-1975, folders 4-5 of 5 (Box 5)
  - Data Processing Steering Committee, 1973-1975 and undated (Box 5)
  - Medical Staff Reports, 1969-1973 and undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Administrative Office Files Series, 1917-1989 (bulk 1930-1976), 2925 items, 4.6 linear feet
  - School of Nursing, 1953-1973 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1935-1940, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1922-1939, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Lincoln Charter, 1917, 1943-1956 (Box 6)
  - Deed giving over Lincoln Hospital land to County of Durham, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Federal Works Administration, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Deeds and Lincoln Charters, 1940s and 1950s (Box 6)
  - Board of Trustees, 1943-1973 (Box 6)
  - Lincoln Hospital log, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Needs, 1971-1973 and undated (Box 6)
  - Periodicals, 1960-1965 (Box 6)
  - Publicity, 1951-1961 (Box 6)
  - Women's Auxilliary, 1954-1976 (Box 6)
  - Directors' Correspondence, 1950-1969 (Box 6)
  - Staff Notes, 1948-1957, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Staff Notes, 1948-1955, 3 folders (Box 6A)
  - Building Committee's Report, 1948-1953 (Box 6A)
  - Publicity (periodicals), 1948-1956 (Box 7)
  - Executive Committee, 1967-1983, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Staff Reports, 1971-1975 (Box 7)
  - Medical Staff Minutes, 1968, 1972-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Staff Reports, 1967-1972 (Box 7)
  - Staff Notes, 1973-1976, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - DCHC Personal Policy Manual, 1989, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Annual Reports: Lincoln Hospital, Lincoln School of Nursing, 1923-1924 (Box 8)
    [Includes annual finance reports and nursing school admissions and superintendent's recommendations for coming year]
  - Board of Trustees: Durham County Hospital Corporation, 1974-1976, 4 folders (Box 8)
    [Includes 1972-1973 Lincoln Hospital Utility Report]
  - Employment and Training, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
  - City of Durham, 1961-1976, 2 folders (Box 8)
    [Includes utilities, fire code, complaints]
  - Durham Advisory Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
  - Dedication Ceremonies, 1952-1953, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - N.C. Medical Care Commission, Raleigh, Quarterly Meeting, December 18, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Lincoln Hospital, Lincoln Hospital Report, circa 1941, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Comprehensive Health Center, circa 1964, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Fire Safety and Regulations, circa 1961-1967 (Box 9)
  - North Carolina Hospital Association, 1974-1976, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Procedures in Record-Keeping for Hospitals, 1963, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Survey of General Hospital Projects Built with Hill-Burton or State Assistance in North Carolina and South Carolina, 1959 (Box 9)
  - A Study of Preadmission Techniques in General Hospitals of North Carolina and South Carolina, 1963 (Box 9)
  - North Carolina State Board of Health, 1948-1976, folder 1 of 2 (Box 9)
  - North Carolina State Board of Health, 1948-1976, folder 2 of 2 (Box 10)
  - Duke University, 1952-1976, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - North Carolina Hospital Association, 1971-1975, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - North Carolina Hospital Association Forms, 1975 and undated (Box 10)
  - Lincoln Hospital Equipment List, undated (Box 10)
  - North Carolina State Department of Administration, 1971-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Medical Staff, 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Intern and Residency Program, 1955-1959 (Box 11)
  - National Association of Health Service Executives (NAHSE), 1973-1976, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Durham County Hospital, 1950, 1970-1974, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Report on fire safety of Lincoln Hospital, 1950 (Box 11)
  - Watts Hospital, 1948-1974 (bulk 1965-1974) (Box 11)
    [Contains recommendations, salary and financial information]
  - Study Committee, Hospital Costs, N.C., 1950-1952 and undated, folders 1-2 of 4 (Box 11)
  - Study Committee, Hospital Costs, N.C., 1950-1952 and undated, folders 3-4 of 4 (Box 12)
  - Andre Vann (Researcher and historian on NCCU History Faculty) 1942-1964, 1993 (Box 12)
  - County of Durham, E.S. Swindell, Jr., 1961-1975, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Nursing Service Correspondence, 1969-1976 (Box 13)
    Includes an undated hisotrical sketch of Lincoln Hospital School of Nursing.
  - Robert W. Johnson Foundation, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Tarheel Hospital Financial Management Association (HFMA) News, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Baptist Hospitals, Inc., 1955, 1963-1964, 1975 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Hospital Association, 1973-1976, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Utilization Review Committee, 1971-1975, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Intensive Care Unit (all types), 1973 (Box 13)
  - Operation Breakthrough, 1964-1973 (Box 13)
- Medical Records Series, 1925-1983 and undated, 1085 items, 6.9 linear feet
  - Open Medical Records Subseries, 1955-1976 and undated
    [Open to research use.]
    - Induced abortion case abstracts, 1967-1976 (Box 13)
    - Monthly case reports (Box 13)
      [Separated from the Operating Room index in Box 17.]
    - Operations performed by residents, 1955-1959 (Box 13)
  - Obstetrical Records Subseries, 1928-1976
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [CLOSED TO USE.]
    - Delivery Room Records
      - 1928-1930, Record of deliveries (Box 14)
      - 1930-1949, Delivery room record, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1949-1955, Delivery record (Box 14)
        [Elizabeth Thorpe OR]
      - 1957-1964, Delivery room record, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1949 Jan. 1 - 1950 Aug. 31, Birth record (Box 15)
      - 1965 Jan. 15 - 1970 July 1, Delivery room register, 2 volumes (Box 15)
    - Birth reports (Box 16)
      - 1939-1970, 13 folders (Box 16)
    - Abortion permit forms
      - 1974-1976 (Box 16)
  - Surgical Records Subseries, 1925-1976
    - Operating Schedule Records
      - 1951 Feb. 1 - 1952 Nov. 3, Operation schedule and record (Box 21)
      - 1952 Nov. 17 - 1954 Aug. 7, Operation schedule and record, 2 volumes (Box 22)
      - 1955 Mar. 5 - Sept. 30, Operation schedule and record (Box 21)
      - 1956 Nov. 1 - 1959 July 6, Record of operations (Box 20)
      - Undated, Operation schedule and record (Box 20)
    - Operating Room Records
      - 1925-1926, Operating room index, 2 volumes (Box 17)
      - 1926 June 16 - 1935 Mar. 26, Record of operations, 2 volumes (Box 19)
      - 1939 May 24- 1945 July 24, Record of operations, 2 volumes (Box 17)
      - 1956 Nov. 1 - 1959 July 6, Record of Operations (Box 20)
      - 1955 July 1 - 1958 June 30, Operations performed by residents (Box 17)
      - 1974 Jan. 3 - 1975 July 31 and 1976 June 22 - Sept. 23, Register of operations (Box 18)
    - Recovery Room Records
      - 1971 Oct. 1 - 1976 Sept. 26, Recovery room record book (Box 19)
  - Discharge Records Subseries, 1925-1972
    - 1928 Jan. 25 - 1933 Aug. 12, Patients' index to file (Box 23)
      [Includes loose paper with records from 1925 between pages 46 and 47.]
    - 1931 Feb. 20 - 1933 Dec. 25, Patients' Index, 2 volumes (Box 23)
    - 1932 Aug. 1 - 1936 Aug. 27 Consultations (Box 23)
    - 1935 Jan. 1 - 1936 Jan. 1, Patients' index (Box 23)
    - 1943 - 1972 and undated, Discharge records and service analysis (Box 23)
    - 1925 July 2 - 1926 Nov. 2, Discharge records (Box 23)
  - Death Records Subseries, 1925-1983 and undated
    - 1968-1976, Death reports, 4 folders (Box 24)
    - 1969-1983 and undated, Burial transit permits (Box 24)
    - 1970-1971, Death notifications (Box 24)
    - 1951-1971, Vital statistics [x-ray, admit/discharge, body release, death certificate], 4 folders (Box 24)
    - 1962-1970, Death notification, disposal permits (Box 24)
      [Also includes deposit slips, 1974-1975]
    - 1970s, Miscellaneous birth and death reports (Box 24)
    - 1925-1933, Undertaker Registry (Box 25)
    - 1956-1976, Register of deaths, 3 folders (Box 25)
  - Medical case number indices (Box 34)
    - 1936 Mar. 3 - 1936 Nov. 20 (Box 34)
    - 1933 June 22 - 1934 Mar. 22 (Box 34)
  - Medical staff minutes, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 34)
  - Medical staff minutes, 1968-1974 and undated (Box 34)
  - North Carolina Hospital Association norms, 1975 (Box 34)
  - Medical staff reports, 1969-1972 and undated (Box 34)
  - Staff reports, 1967-1975, 3 folders (Box 34)
  - Medical staff minutes (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous closed materials (Box 34)
- Financial Records Series, 1941-1976, 689 items, 2 linear feet
  - Accounts payable, 1967 Oct. - 1968 Apr. and undated (Box 26)
  - Accounts receivable, 1967 Oct. - 1968 Apr. and undated (Box 26)
  - Accounts Payable, 1971 Apr. 26 - 1976 Oct. 21, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Account book, O.P.D. Emergency Dept., 1965 May 12 - 1967 Feb. 8 (Box 27)
  - Account book, 1972 June - 1974 Sept. and undated (Box 27)
  - Loose papers, 1960 Oct. - 1975 Apr. and undated, 2 folders (Box 27)
    [Includes: "Distribution of Receipts," "Distribution of Cash Receipts," "Payroll Journal," "Receipts and Income Journal," "Disbursements and Expense Journal"]
  - Lincoln Hospital income statements, 1966-1967, 1970-1974 (Box 28)
  - Lincoln Hospital financial statements, 1956-1957, 1962-1963, 1974-1975 (Box 28)
  - Lincoln Hospital budgets, 1969-1974 (Box 28)
  - Lincoln Hospital Report on Examination, 1970-1973 (Box 28)
  - Trustees' report, 1943-1971 (Box 28)
    [Legal contracts and deeds]
  - Securities, Fidelity Bank, 1941-1958 (Box 28)
  - Board of Trustees, 1950-1973, 3 folders (Box 28)
  - Campaign Fund, 1967-1968 (Box 28)
  - Statements of income and expense, 1970 (Box 28)
  - DCHC Finance Committee, 1970-1976, 5 folders (Box 29)
  - Statements of income and expense, 1944-1960 (Box 29)
  - Charges, 1971-1974 and undated, 2 folders (Box 29)
  - The Doris Duke Foundation, 1950-1968 (Box 29)
- Legal Papers Series, 1901-1975 (bulk 1940-1975), 375 items, .6 linear feet
  - N.C. Medical Care Commission - Application for Donation, 1969 (Box 30)
  - Deed of Lincoln to County of Durham for $10, 1950 March (Box 30)
  - Original charter, 1901 (Box 30)
  - North Carolina Board of Medical Examiners (Dr. Joseph J. Combs, Secretary), 1958-1975 (Box 30)
  - Meeting of Trustees - Mr. Rich - Deed of Property to home, 1940 (Box 30)
  - Certificate of Incorporation and Amendments of Trustees, 1917-1972 (bulk 1940-1950), 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Lincoln Hospital, deeds and Lincoln Charter, 1949 (Box 30)
  - WPA, 1943 (Box 30)
  - Lincoln Hospital, deeds and charters, 1950s (Box 30)
  - Contracts and agreements, 1941-1975, 2 folders (Box 30)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1930-1998 and undated, 80 items, 1.0 linear foot
  - History, 1901-1966, circa 1966 (Box 30)
  - Integration of schools, circa 1955 (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous Lincoln Hospital departmental heads file, undated (Box 30)
  - Wasserman tuberculosis reports, 1930 Nov. 26 - 1933 Oct. 28 (Box 30)
  - Clippings, 1949-1963, 1998 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Duke Endowment Series, 1925-1976 and undated, 850 items, 2.2 linear feet
  - Hospital statistics, 1933-1941 (Box 31)
  - Request for Assistance from the Hospital Section, 1925-1962, 13 folders (Box 31)
  - Request for Assistance from the Hospital Section, 1962-1973, 8 folders (Box 32)
  - Loose materials, undated (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959 (Box 32)
  - Notes on the revision of the Application for Assistance, circa 1965 (Box 32)
  - 1956, 1970-1976, 3 folders (Box 32)
  - Comparative miscellaneous statistics, 1957-1968 (Box 33)
  - Hospital cost and service comparisons, 1941-1958 (Box 33)